video strong
opinions weakly
held and you can decide to spell weekly
with an A or an e weekly as in held
weekly not strongly or held weekly like
every week you're going to change your
opinions um this is a saying that has
been you know popping around the tech
world for a very long time
and I want to talk about it because it
has a lot of significance for the mental
state of a technology professional and I
can't ultimately what this statement is
about is
actually calling out Dogma so what is
Dogma Dogma is the practice of believing
in something so strongly that nothing
can challenge your belief in that thing
and to the point where you will defend
it even when when you're presented with
overwhelming evidence that you're wrong
and we talk about a lot of other you
know mental uh maladies um in other
videos that are related to this
including Dunning Krueger and and um
Anakin syndrome imposter syndrome all of
that but this strong opinions weakly
held is a mantra that kind of emerged
from I think Silicon Valley honestly I
don't know where it came from but the
point of it is very simply Thou shalt
not be dogmatic I did another video on
what it means to become a tech bigot and
it's pretty fair I think to say that
most people who become Tech bigot myself
included have developed a dogmatic
relationship with a specific technology
or approach or idea they cannot release
it uh in the face of new information um
you can make the argument that strong
opinions weakly held is another way to
State uh the fundamental tenants of the
scientific method the scientific method
says that nothing is true nothing is
real Nothing is for sure not even the
law of gravity until there is
substantial evidence and that everything
is up for rethinking now you may say
well what about 1 plus 1 that always
equals two right I'm not saying there
are no absolutes I'm not saying absolute
relativism is is absolute which is you
know completely hypocrit hypocritical
and ironic what I'm saying is that
scientific method which has given us
every
major Discovery in since the dawn of
time and I'm talking to te potential
technologist right now I'm not talking
to people look you can believe in God I
don't want to get go down that rabbit
hole and you can still believe that the
fundamental ideas and the fundamental
beliefs related to technology are up for
debate at anytime so when presented with
new
information you leave your strong
opinion at the door and you create a new
opinion based on the new information
that you have this can backfire on you
uh my the people that I used to Mentor
at one point they started calling me and
I hate saying it flip-flop Rob because I
was
so to quote James from the Bible
battered to and fro by the waves and
tossed by the opinions of by the new
information that I was getting and to
tell you the truth I still don't regret
it one in particular that I'll tell a
story about is get lab versus GI Hub
right giab gitlab and GitHub have been
back and forth um as the premier
solution for Source management and and
cicd and a bunch of things for a very
long time and my opinion about which one
you should use um and which one I use I
mean that's a you know investing in a
source management system takes a
tremendous amount of energy and so you
know to change over to something else is
a pretty big deal you want to make sure
you have a lot of evidence for that
particularly if you're in an
architecture role and if you're getting
into it whether you're a web developer
or you're a backend architect or you're
a senior IT professional doing
architecture for the entire company your
job is to research the direction the
most sustainable direction that provides
the best possible solution to a
problem that is your job you might not
like it it might not jive with what you
want to do in which case you might want
to change jobs to do something else
that's doing the thing you want to do um
the point is is you need to stay focused
and you need to stay with the technology
that's going to deliver the best
solution and that technology is going to
change that there's one thing that's
constant in the world of it it is that
everything changes I mean there's
actually a term for this it's called
framework fatigue and the web World in
particular they invented the idea
because the web Frameworks that were
coming up to to deliver web applications
in particular were changing so rapidly
that people can't even keep up by the
time they deliver a project the
framework that they delivered it in is
now p a and we need to do it in another
framework and then they never did
anything nothing ever gets delivered and
not to mention trying to keep up with
your learning which is the subject of
many other videos that I've made how do
you keep up with all that well you
better at least have Friday's off right
there's a video about that go check it
so strong opinions weekly held
technology changes at a pace that is
absolutely astounding and exhausting and
if you don't allow yourself to change
with the tide and not necessarily the
tide but to like be able to distinguish
but a separate video on this distinguish
between a trend and something that has
roots that's actually going to take um
this is really fundamental and if you
don't learn that skill mentally you will
not survive as a technologist I promise
you if you actually do get good at this
though you will be able to see the waves
coming way before the rest and paddle at
the right time and catch those waves and
ride them all the way into success this
this requires you to be willing and able
to give up your beloved wonderful
technology and to to to leave it and and
that um I'm actually going to quote the
late great Chris NOA on this
uh Chris Nova once tweet run once
tweeted before she passed this was this
was last year or so she once tweeted
that most of us will be coding Ino to be
paid for the rest of our lives but rust
presents A New Hope for the future and I
love Chris and I miss her desperately
and I'm going to
cry because Chris
demonstrated this idea more than most
and although I may have disagreed with
her on particular points about rust and
his
usefulness rust she was able to State
very categorically that no go is good
and we're GNA and this isn't about go
and rust this is about an individual who
get it who got it who was able to change
their opinion about something without
giving up their hope uh and their their
interest in what could be so you know
having a strong opinion about something
with regard to providing in you know a
solution for someone who's giving you
money employing you such as in go which
is what she was saying is totally
different than having a passion and an
opinion about what the future could look
like and in her mind that was rust
particularly for low-level driver stuff
which I totally agree with the point is
is that this amazing technologist who
was actually not allowed into the Google
Organization because she didn't fit the
academic profile of people going into
Google
proceeded to prove the the the idea that
that she was capable of doing all of
these things that she had very strong
opinions and she was very very willing
to change those opinions based on what
new information she had come to her and
for that reason she will remain one of
the most amazing people in in in in my
you know Pantheon of Godlike heroes in
the IT world uh along right there next
to Aaron Schwarz and and and others so
again it's okay to have strong opinions
but be willing to change those opinions
when you're presented with new
information and it is does not make you
a lesser person there doesn't need to be
backfire effect because you were wrong
and you thought you were right right it
takes a bigger person it takes a a much
more strong professional to say I was
wrong about wsl2 it actually really
sucks and and it burned me and like see
we told you I'm like you know what
you're right saying you were right if to
hear the words you were right come out
of an IT
professional pretty rare thing
unfortunately I'm imploring you to be
one of those people be one of the people
who admits when they have new
information and that they made a
decision that was wrong based on less
than all the information and when
presented with new information they
willingly and quickly change their
position that is the way of science it
is the way of progress it is the way of
humanity for those of us who want to
proceede and I encourage you to do it